Jesse A. Udall papers, circa. 1882-1981 (bulk, 1935-1978)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Jesse A. Udall papers, circa. 1882-1981 (bulk, 1935-1978)
MS 311
Udall, Jesse Addison, 1893-1980
This collection is organized into two series: Personal and Family Papers; and Professional Papers. The Personal and Family Papers series includes biographical summaries; clippings documenting honors and personal and family achievements; a few miscellaneous church related items; retirement records and correspondence; certificates and awards from various civic organizations; and correspondence and clippings pertaining to son Addison Udall's World War II experiences.
.75 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Jesse Udall was born on June 24, 1893 in Eagar, Arizona, one of six children of Mormon settlers David King Udall and Ida Hunt. He attended elementary and high schools in St. Johns, Hunt, and Snowflake, Arizona, and graduated in 1914 from Gila Academy (now Eastern Arizona Junior College) in Thatcher, Arizona. In 1917 he wed Lela Lee (1895-1976). They had six children.
Following service as an Army ambulance driver in France during World War I, Udall graduated from the University of Arizona Law School in 1924, and established a private practice in Safford. A Republican, he was elected County Attorney for Graham County, a position he held in 1925 and 1926. Returning to private practice, he served as a state legislator from Graham County from 1931 to 1935. He was elected Graham County Superior Court Judge in November 1938.
In 1926 and 1927, Udall helped organize a National Guard unit, 158th Infantry Company G, in Safford. He became captain of the unit in 1928, and five years later was promoted to major in the Judge Advocate Department. As Lieutenant Colonel in 1942 he was called to active duty in Washington, D. C., where he served as Chief of the Review Section of the Internal Security Division, and later as a member of the Industrial Employment Review Board. Returning to Safford in 1945, Udall resumed his private law practice. He was a member of the Arizona Interstate Stream Commission from 1948 to 1953, and was appointed Graham County Superior Court Judge from 1953 to 1958. He served the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints in the presidency of it's Southern California Mission from 1958 to 1960. He resigned that position when he was appointed to fill the Arizona Supreme Court seat vacated by the death of Levi Udall. He was elected to that seat in 1960, 1964 and 1970, and retired in 1972 due to the poor health of his wife Lela. He served as Chief Justice in 1964 and 1969.
Udall married Lillian Cliff Jenkins in 1977. Throughout his life he was active in the Mormon Church, serving as bishop of Thatcher Ward, president of St. Joseph Stake, and patriarch of Tempe Stake. He was also active in a number of service organizations, including the Boy Scouts and Rotary Club. He died of heart failure on May 11, 1980.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
I. Personal and Family Papers, circa. 1882-1981
II. Professional Papers, 1918-1979
Scope and Content Note
This collection is organized into two series: Personal and Family Papers; and Professional Papers. The Personal and Family Papers series includes biographical summaries; clippings documenting honors and personal and family achievements; a few miscellaneous church related items; retirement records and correspondence; certificates and awards from various civic organizations; and correspondence and clippings pertaining to son Addison Udall's World War II experiences.
The Professional Papers series relates to his military and legal careers, and contains primarily correspondence, clippings, and speeches. Other miscellaneous documents include military orders, certificates, Arizona election results from 1960 to 1970, a list of opinions authored by Jesse Udall, and documents pertaining to the operation of the Arizona National Guard Unit in Safford between 1930 and 1940.
Most of the material in this series covers either the span of Udall's National Guard and subsequent Army involvement, 1930 to 1945, or his tenure on the Arizona State Supreme Court, 1960 to 1972. There is little relating to his legal career prior to 1960. Other events falling within the scope of this subgroup are his service on the Arizona Interstate Stream Commission and a post-retirement effort to persuade some U. S. Congressmen of the merits of purchasing a corridor through Mexico from Arizona to the Gulf of California. This collection contains none of the correspondence or papers generated by Udall in his capacity as lawyer or judge.
Access Terms
Udall, Jesse Addison, 1893-1980 -- Archives
Udall, Lela Lee, 1895-1976
Udall Family -- Archives
Arizona -- Supreme Court
Arizona -- National Guard
Mormons -- Arizona
Judges -- Arizona -- Archives
Clippings
Correspondence
Speeches
Photographs
Separated Material
Some duplicate printed material and six military charge sheets were deaccessioned from the collection. One photo postcard was removed and put into the Arizona Southwest Collection under Fort Tuthill. Three items relating to other Udall family members were transferred to the Special Collections biographical files.
Container List
- Series I: Personal and Family Papers, circa. 1882-1981
  - Biographical information. 1893-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Contains summaries of Udall's life, some in newspaper clippings and some apparently prepared by Udall himself. Also contains bibliographic information.
  - Clippings. 1942-1979 and undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Contains clippings, the bulk from 1960 and later, relating to Udall's awards and speeches. Activities of Lela and son David, as well as members of his extended family, are also included.
  - Addison Udall: Letters and clippings. 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Contains two letters from son Addison while stationed in San Francisco, plus clippings about the war effort in the Pacific.
  - Retirement. 1972, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Contains Udall's letter of resignation from the Supreme Court, his request for retirement benefits, and letters of appreciation and support from friends and associates, most written in early 1972.
  - Miscellaneous church material. 1926-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Contains a membership certificate, a dedicatory service program to the Thatcher Ward Chapel, two clippings on his California Mission presidency, and a program and clipping relating to a Master M Man youth service award.
  - Awards and certificates. 1940-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Contains awards and certificates from various organizations including the Selective Service System, Kiwanis, Boy Scouts, American Judicature Society, and Rotary Club.
  - Photographs. circa. 1882-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Contains one color and twenty-three black and white photographs. The earliest photo of Jesse Udall is from 1912. Included are school photos, family photos, and individual portraits.
- Series II: Professional Papers, 1918-1979
  - Correspondence. 1938-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Mostly incoming letters during his tenure on the Arizona Supreme Court, consisting primarily of congratulatory messages for his initial appointment, elections, and attainment of Chief Justice in 1964. Other correspondence includes invitations, thanks for various public services and personal favors, and a few letters relating to church activities.
  - Materials related to legal profession and service as district and Arizona Supreme Court Judge. 1924-1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Contains certificates (including certificates of nomination), commissions, notice of appointment, and oaths of office. Other items include official election results, miscellaneous campaign material, and a list of opinions authored by Justice Udall.
  - Speeches and article. 1940-1971, and undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Contains typewritten and handwritten texts and notes for speeches and talks given by Udall at holiday gatherings, dedications, church services, club and association meetings, mostly in the 1960s. Also contains background materials of newspaper clippings about famous people and historic events, texts of other people's talks, and information or inspirational material taken from other sources.
  - Clippings. circa. 1930-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    Clippings documenting Udall's legal career, all but one from the period of his tenure on the Arizona Supreme Court. Includes a number of clippings from the 1964 impeachment trial of corporation commissioners, A. P. (Jack) Buzard and E. T. (Eddie) Williams Jr.
  - Arizona National Guard: Safford. 1930-1940 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Contains a few records of the Safford Guard (e.g. a memorandum of agreement), but consists mostly of copies of Bulletins, Memorandums, General Orders, and Special Orders sent to the Safford Guard by the State Adjutant General. The majority of the material dates to 1940.
  - National Guard/U.S. Army: Miscellaneous service records and correspondence. 1918-1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Contains miscellaneous papers including an induction order for WWI, clothing orders, a physical exam record, requests for a change of status, notification of promotion, and orders to proceed. All but the induction order are from the period 1935-1945.
  - Interstate Stream Commission. 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Contains Notices of Appointment, accompanying correspondence, acceptance of his resignation from the Commission, a letter of appreciation, and two clippings.
  - Mexico project. 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Contains background material, two road maps, correspondence, and a written proposal relating to his idea that the United States purchase a corridor through Mexico from Arizona to the Gulf of California.